בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ד yud-daled 14. We
pick up with the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב' yud-gimmel amud-bet and
we're in the middle of a lot of discussions of invalid סכך.
schach. We're now dealing with the issue of מקבל טומאה,
mekabel tumah, things that are susceptible for becoming טמא, tamei, and specifically
with the issue that includes fruit that grows from the tree and
because it's edible, it's food. And the question is what about the
status of the יד, yad, the twigs that are attached to it,
the stems? Are those considered part of the fruit or not in
order for to count them into the quantity of non-kosher סכך schach
if you have fruit hanging from a branch? So this was debated
and the issue here was was that on the one hand if
you cut it for סכך schach you're not interested in the fruit
being connected so it's not considered a יד, yad, it's not considered
an appendage to the fruit. Normally that הלכה halacha of טומאה tumah
is only when you want it connected to the fruit. On the
other hand, the argument could be made that even when you want
it for סכך, schach, you want the fruit on it to weigh
down the סכך schach to keep the סכך schach in place. So
that was a debate of אמוראים Amora'im in terms of the status
of those twigs of the stems when you're cutting the branch down
for סכך. schach. We quoted a ברייתא braita that specifically dealt with
that: palms of big fronds of palm trees with dates attached to
it and so on and seemed to have exactly this debate: when
you have to determine how much סכך schach do you count the
stems or not. So the גמרא Gemara says: Is there a way
to get out of this if you want to claim that everybody
says actually that it is generally not counted? Here we see an
opinion that it is counted. So the גמרא Gemara says, let's look
for that. So רב מנשה בר גדא, Rav Menashe bar Gadda, it
starts with it's about eight lines from the bottom starts with the
word Bar Gadda. מי לימא תנאי? Mi leima tanna'i? So according to
the approach that you would never count the stem of fruit when
you cut it for the sake of סכך schach and you would
never count it as part of the fruit, so let's say here
it's a debate of תנאים tanna'im because you see at least that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does count it as part of the fruit
in the ברייתא braita we quoted. So the גמרא Gemara says, no.
אמר לך רב מנשה: Amar lecha Rav Menashe: דכולי עלמא סבר הקוצץ
לסכך אין לו יד. Dechulei alma savar hakatzer leshach ein lo yad.
Everybody would really agree with me that if you cut down that
palm frond or other types of branches for the purpose of סכך,
schach, the יד, yad, the stem is not part of the fruit,
and there's not a problem of פסול סכך pasul schach because you're
not interested in the fruit. So כי פליגי, Ki pligi, והכא במאי
עסקינן, vehacha bemai askinan, thank you so much. Okay, thank you.
What are we talking about here that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it is part of the fruit? He goes, שקצצן לאכילה ונמלך עליהם
לסיכוך. sheketzatan le'achila venimlach aleihem lesichuch. When it was cut down initially
for the purpose of סכך, schach, everybody would agree that the stem
is not part of the fruit. You're not interested in the fruit.
The case was you cut it down initially the branch because you
wanted to eat the fruit. And when you want to eat the
fruit, that's when we say the classic principle of יד, yad, that
the stem is part of it. Okay, and so that would start
with the idea, so that's what makes the difference: it was cut
specifically for the purpose of fruit and the stem was part of
it. Then you change your mind and you said, heck, let's use
this for סכך. schach. And then the question is does the status
of the יד yad switch now that you are determining you are
giving this thing a different function?
It's a כוונה kavana question.
It's a כוונה, kavana, and if the כוונה kavana we all agree
what the כוונה kavana is, is the כוונה kavana effective or not,
or effectual. אי קצצן, I ketzatan, so the גמרא Gemara says, אי
קצצן לאכילה
מאי טעמא דרבנן? i ketzatan le'achila mai ta'ama derabbanan? So wait a
minute, if you cut it down initially for fruit, what's the reason
that the רבנן Rabbanan would say that now the twig is no
longer considered part of the fruit if that was your initial intent?
וכי תימא קסברי רבנן כיון דנמלך עליהם לסיכוך בטלה ליה מחשבתו, Vechi
teima kasavri rabbanan keivan denimlach aleihem lesichuch batlo leih machshavto,
that maybe this is exactly the issue: now that you changed your
mind after it's been cut down, this branch, and you want to
use it for סכך, schach, your initial intent is negated and now
it's identified differently and therefore the stem is no longer part of
the
fruit? ומי בטלה ליה מחשבה? Umi batla leih machshava? והתנן, Vahatnan, we
taught in the משנה, mishna, this is a general principle about intent
when it comes to defining something as a vessel or here as
a stem as part of a fruit for purposes of מקבל טומאה.
mekabel tumah. כל הכלים, Kol hakelim, top of י"ד עמוד א', yud-daled
amud-alef, יורדים לידי טומאה במחשבה. yordim liydei tumah bemachshava.
All כלים kelim literally descend into טומאה tumah with thought. Now it
doesn't literally well descend is an interesting phrase but anyway it doesn't
mean that they become טמא. tamei. What it means is there's a
range of things in the world that naturally are considered fit for
becoming טמא. tamei.
Food that is not fruit that's not attached to the tree that
has had water come in contact with it. Or let's say you
have a completely finished vessel, like you have a, you know, you've
got a spoon, a fork, or something like that. You know, that
automatically becomes טמא. tamei. That's a vessel. But there's a range of
things where there's an ambiguity. ambiguous status of them. Are they finished
yet or not? Which category do they fall in or not? And
that status is determined based on your intent. So what would be
those things? Well, the classic example is, you're in the process of
making a vessel, but it's not clear yet, are you done making
it or not? You've just fashioned out this beautiful spoon from this
piece of metal. Are you done or not? Well, maybe you're going
to make some filigree on the top and you know, finish some
carvings. At what stage is it complete? Okay, that is a question.
Or you are you you know, you have רשי Rashi gives the
example of you have tanned and prepared this nice big thing of
leather. Now, as it is right now, you can use it as
a mat. But is that what its use is? Is it going
to be a mat? Are you going to make strips out of
it and use and cut a shoe out of it? Right, at
what stage is it considered a complete vessel is not self-evident, is
not objectively determinable in most cases. It's a question about what your
intent is. So this is the principle that all the
vessels ירדו לטומאה yerdu letumah go down into טומאה, tumah, become
susceptible במחשבה. bemachshavah. Once you have the intent and you say, you
the maker, the owner of it says, "I'm done now. I'm going
to use this piece of leather as a mat," now it's defined
as a vessel, as a mat, even though you if you were
planning on making shoes, it would not yet be a vessel. But
they become, they get their identity and become susceptible for טומאה tumah
just with your thought. ואין עולים מטומאתן אלא בשינוי מעשה. ve'ein olim
mitumatan ella beshinuy ma'aseh.
But they cannot change their status except with an action. So, if
I went ahead and took this piece of leather and I decided
I was going to make it a mat, and I said, "You
know what? I think I'm actually going to make shoes out of
it." It doesn't now stop being able to be טמא, tamei, right?
It once its identity takes place, even though that was only through
thought, not through action, right, you cannot keep on switching it on
and off and change your mind on and off. Once its identity
is now it's a vessel, it can't change that identity until you
actually do an action to it. Now if you start cutting it
and making it and, you know, cutting it for for shoes and
cutting out a new shape and then, okay, it's no longer a
mat. Now it's in the process of being made for shoes and
it no longer can become טמא. tamei. So your thought can give
it its initial identity, but your thought cannot change it once it
gets that identity, and to change it then would require an action.
So if I have a pelt, right, and I intend to make
it into a mat, and it's not a mat yet because it
hasn't been finished, right, but that's already in the status of something
that will be מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah?
No, if you intend to make it into a mat and it's
not yet complete as a mat, then it's not מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah.
It's only when it's complete. Only when it's complete.
But once your thought has identified it as complete and given its
identity as a vessel, right, so then, it's not like it starts
life becoming, you know, a vessel. It gets its identity through your
thought, but once it's identified as a vessel, it won't lose that
identity until you actually do an action to it. Okay. So,
מעשה מוציא מידי מעשה, ma'aseh motzi midei ma'aseh, an action can negate
an action. If I cut it into the perfect shape of a
mat, I made it and and I was done, I made it
into a mat with an action. But if I do another counter-action,
I start cutting that into into a shape for a shoe, then
that redefines it. So an action is strong enough to change a
prior action, ומעל מחשבה, umi'al machshavah, and certainly strong enough to change
just the thought. If I just decided I was going to keep
it as a mat, even without associating it with an action, right,
but if you need an action can reverse whatever identity it has,
whether it got that initial identity through thought or through an action.
A new action redefines something.
מחשבה, machshavah, but a thought, a new thought to change its identity,
אינה מוציאה לא מידי מעשה ולא מעל מחשבה, einah motzia lo midei
ma'aseh velo mi'al machshavah, is not strong enough, certainly not to counter
an action, if you had cut it as the shape of a
mat, and now you just think, "Hey, I'll make it a shoe,"
you know, obviously thought loses against the prior action. But not only
that, it even loses against the prior thought. A thought is not
so strong. So what a thought can do is it can take
something, here's a good way of thinking about it, it can take
something in an ambiguous state with an ambiguous identity and nail down
its identity, give it identity. But once something has an identity, your
thought is not meaningful against that status already and that clear identity.
The only thing that can change it is an action. Okay. But
I can go around the room thinking about a million things I'm
going to do, right, you know, but it doesn't actually give it
change something the way something is until you actually act on it.
The only power of the thought is when something has an ambiguous
identity. So that is the basic principle. So now we've got our
question. That's true about a vessel. We have something else that has
an ambiguous identity for טומאה, tumah, which is the stem of a
fruit. Is it considered a יד yad to the fruit, part of
the fruit, serving the fruit or separate? So, the גמרא Gemara assumes
presumably the same הלכה halacha would be true. If I cut it...
cut down the branch and wanted to use the fruit, to eat
the fruit, and that made the stem part of it, now, so
that was an initial act, plainly an act and a thought, okay,
anyway, my intent was to eat the fruit, that gave the stem
its identity as part of the fruit, now if I decide heck,
I'll use it for סכך, s'chach, why should that have the power
to change its identity, its identity has already been fixed?
But you can't use the fruit for סכך. s'chach.
But you cannot use the fruit for סכך. s'chach. But you want
to put the whole branch on the סוכה sukkah with the fruit.
Okay. Well, so where does the stem get counted? Part of the
fruit? The fruit is, yeah, or whatever, it's there, as the גמרא
Gemara said before, to weigh it down. But where does the stem
get counted in the category of כשר סכך kosher schach or the
פסול? pasul? So it says now that you change your mind, how
could that change the identity of the stem? That's a new thought
coming to change something whose identity was already fixed.
But how about some kind of מעשה ma'aseh would use? Putting it
on the סוכה. sukkah. Exactly. Okay, so maybe your מעשה ma'aseh in
the סוכה.
sukkah. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara seems that that's not a sufficient
מעשה. ma'aseh.
Well, what מעשה ma'aseh would you do?
I don't know, this is kind
of but that
then makes it a moot point. So some things there might not
be a good option other than really changing it. Okay, but yeah,
it is a good point that you say that the putting it
on the סוכה sukkah is not considered to be a מעשה. ma'aseh.
We're going to see in a minute other things that are not
enough of a changing of the thing. Remember, if the classic example
is the piece of leather, then the מעשה ma'aseh physically changes it,
just doesn't do something with it or to it, it actually physically
changes. Let's say I would pick up, here, you want a similar
example? Let's say I take this thing that's been a mat and
that's been on the ground, and I pick it up and I
move it to my workbench, okay, where where I have all my
leather tools. Does that change its identity? That's your idea, I put
it on my סוכה. sukkah. Fine, you moved it, but you haven't
done something significant to change its identity.
Because in the case of the סכך, s'chach it is in the
place to serve as סכך. s'chach, What we had earlier, יד הבא
מן המחשבה. yad haba min hamachshava. Right. All right, it's a good
question. It's a good question. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes
with it, okay? The גמרא Gemara is going to say that maybe
it works, but not for the reason that Michael just said, which
is a very good point. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
וכי תימא v'chi teima הני מילי hani mili כלים דחשיבי. keilim dechashivei.
When is it that your thought can't change its an identity? When
it has the status of a כלי, kli, of a vessel? That
is a significant identity, and therefore your thought now won't just change
it; you need an action. אבל ידות, aval yadot, but a simpler
question of the of a twig, is it serving the food, fruit,
or is it not serving the fruit? It's not a thing about
like the identity of the object; it's more like functional, you know,
where is it associated with? דלצורך אכילה נינהו, dil'tzorech achila ninhu, that's
only a question of it's serving the eating or not serving the
eating; it's not like the identity of the twig, you know. There's
a question of what function are you using it with? These are
the stems, the stems I should be saying. מחשבה משויא ליה ומחשבה
מפקיא ליה. machshava mashvia lei umachshava mafkia lei. Maybe a thought gives
it one function, the stem to serve the fruit, and another thought
gives it another function. It's not serving the fruit, it's not a
major identity issue of the stem that needs an action to redefine
it. So that's a pretty good way of distinguishing between the two.
The גמרא Gemara says no, ותנן, v'tnan, we taught in the משנה
Mishna in עוקצין, Uktzin, which talks about this issue of יד, yad,
כל ידות האוכלים, kol yadot ha'ochlim, all the stems or the ידות
yadot of
food, שביססן בגורן, shebissasan bagoren, that you were ביססן bissasan in a
גורן. goren. Now what ביססן bissasan means is going to be a
big debate in a minute, okay? But let's take a look.
So so one explanation of ביססן bissasan is you like undid the
bundle, okay? You you the other word explanation of ביססן bissasan is
like you sort of threshed, okay? So so so you were ביססן
bissasan them in the threshing floor. טהורות, tehorot, are טהור. tahor.
And רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi said this טמא, tamei, although the גמרא
Gemara later is going to quote the end, it seems like it
hasn't quoted the end yet. Okay, so that's the הלכה. halacha. You
have this bundle of wheat and you were, now what is the
יד yad for a wheat? The יד yad for the wheat is
the straw, is the stem. That's not the actual food itself, but
it supports it. What do you use that stem for? You don't
eat the wheat like you don't hold like a twig of an
apple, you know, the stem of an apple. What what do you
use that stem for in the wheat case? How does it serve
the purpose? Can you think about how that stem helps serve the
purpose of the wheat? Yeah, like you carry it, exactly. You bundle
up a bundle of wheat, and you're using the straw to make
a
שיפא, shipa, right, a שיפא shipa is something else, to make a
sheaf, and that helps you carry it, right? So that's the way
the יד yad serves the wheat. So now you take this bundle
of wheat into your threshing floor and you undo the bundle, and
it all falls. Now right now what are you going to do?
You're going to bring in your cows, you're going to thresh it,
okay, you're going to turn it, you know, you're going to separate
the kernel from the chaff and so on. Do you need the
straw anymore? Not really, right? The straw is just going to get
in the way. So the moment you undid the bundle, you now
no longer need that יד. yad. So what so there's going to
be one interpretation that the word ביססן bissasan means you un you
undid them, okay, and that changes their identity. Okay, so this this
straw had served the food, you now undo the bundle, you have
no longer any need for it, it stops serving the food, it
no longer is a יד. yad. So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara does. with it. בשלמא למאן דאמר ביססן, Bishlama
le-man de-amar bisasan, it makes sense if the word ביססן bisasan means
התיר אגודן, hitir agudan, you undid the knots, the bundle, שפיר. shafir.
That's a good proof. Why is it a good proof? Because the
גמרא Gemara says and Michael this addresses your issue, this is just
like the case of the סכך. s'chach. You didn't physically change the
piece of wheat. You didn't do an action to the piece of
the wheat
directly, but you did something with it so that now it's clear
you no longer need the stem. You undid the bundle in the
threshing floor, that makes it clear you no longer need the stem.
So that would show that a מחשבה machshava or if you want,
a מחשבה machshava with doing an act with something, but not to
something, is sufficient. The stem was part of the wheat, you undid
the bundle, it's no longer halachicly considered part of the wheat, just
like the סכך, schach. you wanted the stem with the fruit with
the food, you moved the סכך schach, to the top of your
סוכה, sukkah, you decided to make it into סכך, schach and now
it changes its identity. That is analogous and the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, we see there that that type of a thing would work
even though it's not done to the object, just with the object.
That would be good. אלא למאן דאמר מאי ביססן Ela le-man de-amar
mai bisasan but according to the approach that ביססן bisasan means something
else, ביססן ממש, bisasan mamash, literally ביססן, bisasan, what does that mean?
רש"י Rashi says it means thresh them. If you take a look
in רש"י Rashi he gives you how this word ביססן bisasan could
mean these different things. Anyway, but if it means that he literally
began to thresh it, which is changing the wheat itself, you're threshing
the wheat, so מאי איכא למימר, mai ika le-meimar, what can you
say? Because only when you actually physically change it does the יד
yad change its identity. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי
דביססן ממש. hacha nami de-bisasan mamash. So here too in the case
of the
סכך schach, one minute. Oh no, it's rhetorical one minute. הכי נמי
דביססן ממש. hacha nami de-bisasan mamash. You actually did a similar type
of a thing when you decided to I mean רש"י Rashi doesn't
describe what exactly that scenario would be, but you decided to actually
make this branch into סכך, schach you did something, maybe you know
maybe you pressed it down, you flattened it, you did something physical
to the branch itself in order to use it as סכך. schach,
So the גמרא Gemara says that's what you did. אי הכי I
hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, מה טעמייהו דאחרים, ma tameihu de-acherim, what's
the reason of the others that say that it still
does not change its identity? So דאמר כרבי יוסי, de-amar ke-Rabbi Yossi,
fine, like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi did not we taught in the
משנה, Mishna, רבי יוסי מטמא, Rabbi Yossi metamei, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says that even when you thresh the wheat, the straw remains part
of it. So you want to say that if the word here
means threshing it and you need actual physical to change it in
order to change the status of the יד, yad, so similarly when
we were talking about the fronds of palm with the dates on
it, it would only change its status of the יד yad when
you physically changed it. So Michael said before what would you do
to physically change it? And the גמרא Gemara says you did something,
you beat it down, you flattened it, you did something to make
it more into סכך. schach. And that's why the יד yad changes
its status. But if that's true, why would there be the debate?
Why would רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אחרים acherim say that it doesn't
change its status? Ah, it says no we have like רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yossi, just like over here by the threshing that it doesn't
change the status, there it would be the same thing. One minute.
היי מאי, Hai mai, how could you compare it? בשלמא התם טעמיה
דרבי יוסי חזיא Bishlama hatam tameih de-Rabbi Yossi chazya לכדרבי שמעון בן
לקיש. ke-de-Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish.
There it's different. There the reason רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says even
when you thresh it, the straw is still part of it is
because the straw still serves a purpose. What purpose does it serve
once you started threshing it? Like what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said.
דאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, De-amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, הואיל וראוי
להופכן באתרא, hoil ve-raui le-hofchan be-attara, since you can upturn it with
a pitchfork, right? Even after you begin to thresh the wheat, the
straw is functional because if
you want to turn it upside down and thresh it from the
other side, move it around, you're going to use a pitchfork and
the straw will help for that.
אלא הכא למאי חזיא, Ela hacha le-mai chazya, but what is it
any good for here?
It has a use. It has a
use because it's become enough. Right. Because what you could theoretically do.
Right. So here's the case. I think we were probably getting a
little bit lost but let me see if I can help a
little with some props. Okay, here are your big palm fronds. Right,
I don't know what a palm frond looks like with a little
whatever. You know with your dates attached to it, right? Okay, and
the question is what is the status of the יד? yad?
Does that count with the כשר סכך kosher schach, or the פסול
סכך? pasul schach?
Okay, so we want to say now if we're trying to say
that in a normal case יד yad is always part of the
כשר סכך, kosher s'chach, what is the debate here? The debate here
originally it was cut for אכילה, achila, so originally when it was
לצורך אכילה, le-tzorech achila, this was a יד, yad, okay? And now
you changed your mind and you want to use it for סכך
schach. and does that change the status? All right, that's the question.
It's an interesting thing. You know the dates don't grow from the
fronds, they grow from the trunk.
Very all right.
You're maybe it's something from the trunk.
All right, you know what... Too much for me right now. Okay,
so we're comparing that to this case. Okay, in this case, this
is the יד, yad, right? Mr. Wheat? This is my wheat, my
bundle of wheat, that's the יד, yad, right? Okay, and it starts
off having that status, like this, it started off having the status,
right? And then it changed. Is it going to change? So what's
the scenario to that's a debate, right? The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
says here that it's טהור, tahor, not a יד, yad, and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that it's טמא tamei which means it is
a יד. yad. Okay, and here too, the debate is as the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said that it is כשר סכך, kosher schach.
which means not a יד, yad, and אחרים Acherim say that it
is the יד yad is פסול, pasul, which means that it is
a יד. yad. Okay? So we have two debates. We want to
figure out what the debate is. So the גמרא Gemara says, ah,
first answer actually works very good, because the first answer describes that
this scenario, what did you do here? So here it went from
you cut it down for the purpose of אוכל ochel and then
you decided to use it for סכך, schach okay, that was your
מחשבה. machshava. You started with that and you moved. And here what
did you do? It started naturally as the יד, yad, what changed?
What changed was so according to one version, בשסן bisasan means you
undid the knot. Okay? So one says בי, bey, that's great, the
parallel, because you didn't do anything to the thing itself, the same
way here you just had a new thought, okay, maybe you put
it up on top of your סוכה. sukkah. You did something with
it, but not to it. Here too, you undid the knot, you
had a new thought, you didn't really do something with it but
not to it. And we have the debate here whether it has
the status of יד, yad, we have a debate here whether it
keeps the status of whether that status will change when you had
a new thought and did something with it without doing something to
it. It's a very nice parallel debate. Okay? But the גמרא Gemara
says, but no, there's another opinion that says everybody would agree that's
not enough. And what's happening here is, I have to draw my
cow, okay, whatever, you actually started threshing it. Okay, cow looks like
a big piece of wheat. Anyway, you actually started threshing it. And
that's what the that's what happens here. Okay, so what's the parallel?
You actually have to do something to it. So fine, we'll say
you didn't just have a new thought, you actually beat it down
and did something to it to more physically make it סכך. s'chach,
So now we've made them parallel, okay? It's not just a new
מחשבה, machshava, there's actually some physical act. You did something physical to
make it into סכך. s'chach. Now but now we have a question.
If that's true, you actually did something physical, wouldn't everybody agree that
this changes? What's the story? So the גמרא Gemara says here we
understand why there could still be a debate, because even though you
did something physical, you might still want the straw to, you know,
to use the pitcher to turn it over. But here once you've
done something physical, how could there still be a debate? Why would
anybody say you want this to be part of the fruit? You're
now using this as סכך. s'chach.
So when would you not have to worry
about the you might never until you actually started sifting it or
something, you might never not have to worry as long as it's
attached. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, so now we understand how you're
making a parallel, in both cases you did something physical, not just
with it but to it, but what's the logic that the stem
should still be part of the fruit if you're actually going to
use it for סכך? s'chach. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
הכא למאי חזיא? ela hacha lemai chazya? What's the stem still going
to be used for? What's it fit for, now that, you know,
for why would it want to be part of the fruit? גמרא
Gemara says חזיא לכסאא למינתליה בגילאי. chazya lechisasa lemi'intelei bigila'ei.
No, it's fit because סוכות Sukkos isn't going to last forever, so
when סוכות Sukkos is over and you undo your סוכה, sukkah, then
you're going to want to, you know, to pick it up with
the stem. So basically the point is, you know what, it's you
still got the fruit attached to your frond or wherever it's attached
to,
and you want the stem because you initially planned to use it
for fruit, so just because the fruit is attached now doesn't mean
you're after סוכות Sukkos you're not going to cut it off and
go back to using it for fruit. So therefore it still is
considered to be part of בגילאי. bigila'ei. רש"י Rashi says it means
just like with the straw, with the stem. Okay.
So in sum, basically the whole debate is can we use the
stems or not for סכך s'chach? because stems may
or may not be part of the fruit, therefore possibly to get
טמא. tamei. Exactly. And the and the whole question is under what
circumstances is it no longer part of the fruit because you don't
need the handle and what constitutes what physical act needs to take
place that people disagree. Exactly.
That is an excellent summary. Correct. And the only reason here if
we actually did a physical act that we would still consider part
of the fruit just because סוכות Sukkos isn't going to last forever
and when סוכות Sukkos is over you're still going to want it
as part of the fruit.
This is important what we can do, you means
like how do
you
you don't want it part of the fruit?
You might not have a choice.
That's what I'm saying.
Okay, you might not not everything is possible in the world
when you're comparing the edible and non-edible portions. Exactly. How do you
value the stems? That was the question, which side do they fall?
Exactly.
Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: גופא, Gufa,
let's go back and look at this statement as we said before.
כל ידות האוכלין שבשסן בגורן טהורות ורבי יוסי מטמא. Kol yadous ha'ochlin
shebisasan bagoren tehoros v'Rabbi Yosi metamei. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: גופא. Gufa. Let's go back and look at this statement
as we said before: כל ידות האוכלין שביססן בגורן טהורות, Kol yadot
ha-ochlin she-bisasan bagoren tehoros, רבי יוסי מטמא. Rabbi Yose metamei. Okay, so
this is exactly this issue. Once you do this ביססן bisasan in
the threshing floor, are the stems, are the, is the straw still
considered to be a יד yad or not? חכמים Chachamim say no
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says it is. מאי ביססן? Mai bisasan?
What does this mean? רבי יוחנן אומר ביססן ממש, Rabbi Yochanan omer
bisasan mamash, literally you threshed it. רבי אלעזר אומר היתר אגדן. Rabbi
Elazar omer hitar agdan. No, it's enough to just undo the knots
and there already that would change the status.
Okay. בשלמא לרבי אלעזר דאמר ביססן היתר אגדן היינו טעמא דמטמא רבי
יוסי. Bishlama le-Rabbi Elazar de-amar bisasan hitar agdan hainu ta'ama de-metamei Rabbi
Yose. Now we understand that's a big חידוש chiddush that just not
even physically changing it, just undoing the knot changes the status of
the stem, now you can, of the straw, you can understand why
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would go along with that. אלא לרבי יוחנן
דאמר ביססן ממש אמאי מטמא רבי יוסי? Ella le-Rabbi Yochanan de-amar bisasan
mamash amai metamei Rabbi Yose? We're just recapping what we said before,
right? But now doing it with not with a, using it as
a proof but a focus on this debate itself. If you actually
threshed it, why would the straw still be considered part of the
wheat? אמר שמעון לקיש עברוהו להפכן בעתר Amar Shimon Lakish avruhu le-haphchan
be-attar because it's fit to upturn them with a pitchfork.
The point was just to now directly show the debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. Before we referred to it, here we're sort of quoting it
directly. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, said Rabbi Elazar, למה נמשלו
תפילתם של צדיקים כעתר? Lamma nimshalu tfilasam shel tzaddikim ke-attar? Why is
the prayer, ויעתר יצחק להשם לנוכח אשתו ויעתר לו השם, vaye'etar Yitzchak
l'Hashem le-nochach ishto vaye'aser lo Hashem, right? So why does ויעתר, vaye'etar,
which is a word for a pitchfork, I don't know if it's
a biblical word for a pitchfork, I didn't check, but anyway, I,
it probably, it probably is. Anyway, why is that the same word
used for supplication and prayer? לומר לך מה עתר זה מהפך את
התבואה בגורן, Lomar lach ma attar zeh mehaph-chesh hat-vuah ba-goren, the same
way a pitchfork turns, you know, you use it to turn over
the wheat in a threshing floor ממקום למקום, mi-makom le-makom, you carry
it from one place to another place, אף תפילתן של צדיקים מהפכת
דעתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא ממידת אכזריות למידת רחמנות. af tfilatan shel
tzaddikim mehapa-ches da'ato shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu mi-middas achzariyus le-middas rachamanus. The
prayer of righteous turns God's, you know, desire and God's attributes from
that of cruelty, it's actually quite a harsh phrase to use, I
normally say מידת הדין, middas hadin, here מידת אכזריות middas achzariyus cruelty
to that of compassion, למידת רחמנות. le-middas rachamanus. What?
I understand but it's interesting to use the phrase אכזריות. achzariyus. It's
quite fascinating, right, to turn over, to like, you know, to imagine
that what you're doing is, your prayers are, you know, are reversing
and turning something over, turning it over.
Talk about the efficacy of prayer.
Well, yeah, the גמרא Gemara often has things like that about the
efficacy, but the metaphor, the imagery is powerful too. Okay, so let's
keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like this. You know, I'll
just say very quickly, there's a fascinating רש"י Rashi here, it maybe
is actually more of a gloss in רש"י Rashi because there's some,
there's some debate about,
about, it seems sometimes within our רש"יs Rashi we have some glosses
of a student. So if you take a look here, it says
like this, it says
four lines down in the wide lines, about a third into the
line, you see where it says שאלתי את מורי? sha'alti es Mori?
Yeah, that's not the standard לשון lashon of רש"י, Rashi, this is
probably the student saying, שאלתי את מורי מגופא דמשנה. sha'alti es Mori
mi-gufa de-mishna. It says גופא gufa and then it quotes
the משנה. mishna. דמייתי אגב גררה בשמעתין. De-maisi agav grara bi-shmaitin. It
had sort of indirectly quoted the משנה mishna and then you're going
to say גופא gufa and go back to the whole משנה mishna
and look at it
in whole. So by the way, do people understand, appreciate the difference
between גופא Gufa and אמר מר? Amar Mar? I think I've said
this before. Okay. גופא Gufa and אמר מר Amar Mar are two
ways of looking at something that has been quoted before and analyzing
it. Something that was quoted in the middle of a debate, going
back and looking at it and analyzing it. The difference is is
that גופא Gufa is when we quoted a portion of of something
and now we're going to sort of like quote it in whole
and then look at it. Okay. אמר מר Amar Mar is when
we maybe quoted the whole thing but now we're going to sort
of select some lines out to look at it. Okay. So here
he's saying, he described that, he says דמייתי אגב גררה בשמעתין, de-maisi
agav grara bi-shmaitin, this משנה mishna was brought indirectly in the middle
and then we're going to say גופא gufa and go back to
the whole משנה mishna and look at it in whole. מי שייך
למיתני גופא כי
דגרסינן במימרות אמוראים? Mi shayach le-misnei gufa ki de-garsinan be-meimras amora'in? Why
would you say גופא gufa which is normally something we do in
like a amoraic statement, which is pretty funny, but he probably means
what's more something that we do often with, you know, בריתות baraitas
or it's rare that we, apparently I haven't checked this out, apparently
we don't say גופא gufa by a משנה, mishna, we use, we
say גופא gufa by like a בריתא baraita or an amoraic statement
we were going back to but not a משנה. mishna. ואמר לי
רבי משום דהך משנה מן הטהרות שאין מהם גמרא בעולם ולא מפורשת
כשאר משניות ועל כן הוצרך לומר גופא כדי לפרש. Ve-amar li Rebbi
mishum de-hach mishna min ha-taharos she-ein me-hem Gemara ba-olam velo mefu-reshes keshar
mishnayos ve-al ken hu tzarich le-mar gufa kedei le-phareish.
Meaning
the basic point is, why would we say גופא gufa to explicate
a משנה? mishna? Just talk about the משנה mishna when you get
to it. Get, you know, when you, so if we quoted a
משנה mishna in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, we wouldn't say גופא gufa
and look at it here, we'll explain that משנה mishna when we
get to בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Why are we saying גופא? gufa?
He says, oh because it's a משנה mishna in טהרות, Taharos, nobody
ever learns טהרות. Taharos. גופא gufa because it's a משנה mishna in
טהרות Taharas and there's no גמרא Gemara in טהרות. Taharas. So if
we're going to quote a משנה mishna in טהרות, Taharas, the only
place to look at it would be here now that we've quoted
it. Okay, but it is fascinating that like
historical sensitivity to how גופא gufa is used and the historical question
and so on. By the way, though, what was I going to
say?
Yeah, so you can check this. I don't know, but apparently according
to this other than you know, גופא gufa is never used by
a משנה mishna so that could be something you could check. I'm
by the way just seeing here if we can figure out if
I'm going to do a Bar-Ilan search if עטרה atara is a
biblical word. Hold on one sec. Not that one.
עטרה atara is
in
four.
Yeah, עתר atar meaning fork. Yeah, exactly.
Let's see if that's a biblical word that happens to be mentioned
in עדר. Eider.
Was it what? עדר. Eider.
עין דלת ריש? Ayin Dalet Resh?
Oh, for a pitchfork. I just checked
this quickly.
Is it in JOS? Yes, what does JOS say?
JOS says it's עתר atar
meaning pitchfork to describe the prayer of יצחק Yitzchak and רבקה. Rivka.
Right. As you can see they show you know about the right.
The word's actually used as
pitchfork. Oh that okay, that's a picture there.
Okay,
of a pitchfork.
Oh interesting it only has two, it's not like our pitchfork with
a lot of tines.
Like a pickle fork.
Okay,
well I just tried to do a search and I'm oh, it's
in the middle of working on it. Oh, because I didn't limit
it to תנ"ך Tanach so it's going through like everything in the
world. All right, anyway let's keep on going. Let's get to the
עטרות ודיבון. Atarot v'Divon. That doesn't help us. Right. עטרות, Atarot, עטרות.
Atarot. Hold on let's see. Is it in יהושע? Yehoshua? And the
oh, here's ויהי דוד נחפז ללכת מפני שאול ושאול ואנשיו עוטרים אל
דוד ואל אנשיו לתפסם. v'hi David nechpaz lalechet mipnei Shaul v'Shaul v'anashav
otrim el David v'el anashav l'tofsam.
So that means like I don't know, chasing after something.
והיה עטרת תפארת,
v'haya ateret tiferet,
that's a crown. בהרם העטרה, Ba'aram ha'atara,
בעטרת תפארת. ba'ateret tiferet.
It does not look like what?
Oh that's with a ט, tes, right. Oh, I put it in
wrong. All right, we'll have to look it up later. No wonder
I'm getting the wrong word. I put it in with a ט.
tes. All right, let's go on. Let's look at the משנה. mishna.
מסככין בנסרים דברי רבי יהודה. Mesachin b'nisarin divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
So you can use planks of wood for your סכך. s'chach So
you can. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said. רבי
מאיר אוסר Rabbi Meir oser and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir forbids it.
Because we'll see, but the most obvious reason is even though it's
a plank of wood it's like a 2x4, right, and it's totally
not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, it grows from the ground. Four fingers
wide? Well we'll see how wide it is. But basically it's very
nice that it's כשר סכך, kosher schach. but it looks like a
roof. You got straight planks of wood up on your roof. נתן
עליה נסר שהוא רחב ארבעה טפחים, Natan aleha neser shehu rachav arba
tefachim, now if you did put a plank of wood ארבעה טפחים
arba tefachim on your roof, כשרה, keshera, the סוכה sukkah can remain
כשרה keshera ובלבד שלא יישן תחתיו, uvilvad shelo yishan tachtav, don't
sleep under it. And the idea would be like we've seen before
that's talking if it's juxtaposed to the wall because then it's like
a bending the wall. So there even though it's פסול סכך pasul
s'chach, it will be כשר kasher if it's directly adjacent to the
wall but you can't sleep under it because now it gets a
status of a wall and it no longer has a status of
סכך. schach.
You didn't say
it's next to the wall. I know but that's what רש"י Rashi
says and that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say although
not here later. אמר רב, Amar Rav, says רב, Rav, מחלוקת בנסרים
שיש בהן ארבעה. machlokes b'nisarin sheyesh bahen arba'ah. The debate of can
you use planks of wood is if they're ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim
wide, about a foot wide. דרבי מאיר אית ליה גזירת תקרה, d'Rabbi
Meir isleh gzeirat tikrah, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can't because
it looks too much like a ceiling, a normal ceiling. ורבי יהודה
לא אית ליה גזירת תקרה, v'Rabbi Yehuda lo isleh gzeirat tikrah, and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't hold of that.
אבל בנסרים שאין בהן ארבעה, aval b'nisarin she'ein bahen arba'ah, but if
it's not ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim wide, דברי הכל כשרה, divrei hakol
keshera, everybody would agree that it's כשרה keshera because nobody would think
that that constitutes yet a like significant plank and it doesn't look
like a roof. ושמואל אמר u'Shmuel amar and שמואל Shmuel says no,
בשאין בהן ארבעה מחלוקת, b'she'ein bahen arba'ah machlokes, they debate even smaller
than ארבעה, arba'ah, even less than ארבעה טפחים. arba tefachim. אבל יש
בהן ארבעה, aval yesh bahen arba'ah, but once it's ארבעה טפחים, arba
tefachim, דברי הכל פסולה, divrei hakol psula, everybody would say it's פסולה.
psula. Meaning everybody holds of the גזירת תקרה gzeirat tikrah that you
fundamentally cannot use a plank of wood that looks like a roof.
The only debate is how big of a plank begins to be
a problem. Everybody agrees ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim is a problem. What
about less than ארבעה טפחים? arba tefachim? So Rav says בשאין בהן
ארבעה b'she'ein bahen arba'ah is a problem.
פחות משלושה, pachas m'shlosha, how less? Like even less than שלושה טפחים?
shlosha tefachim? הקני בעלמא הוא, hakani b'alma hu, it's just a stick!
You call every piece of wood you call it a plank? There's
got to be a range in which it's a problem. אמר רב
פפא הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Pappa hachi ka'amar, here's what he means.
יש בהן ארבעה דברי הכל פסולה, yesh bahen arba'ah divrei hakol psula,
once it's ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim everybody holds from everybody holds of
this גזירת תקרה. gezeiras tikra.
פחות משלושה, pachos mishlosha, less than three, דברי הכל כשרה. divrei hakol
kashera. Everybody would agree it's okay because that is just a stick.
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? קני בעלמא הוא, kani b'alma hu, and it's
just a stick. כי פליגי משלושה ועד ארבעה, ki pligi mishlosha v'ad
arba'a, the debate according to this approach is everybody agrees of the
גזירת תקרה, gezeiras tikra, the debate is how big. Four is certainly
a problem. Between three and four, that's the debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. מר סבר, mar savar, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would hold, one would hold, כיון דלית ביה שיעור
מקום לא גזרינן, keivan d'les beih shiur makom lo gazrinan, less than
four טפחים tfachim is not yet the size of a space. Remember
we discussed this idea before, particularly by like רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
What's a minimal רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid? Four טפחים tfachim by four
טפחים tfachim with a wall ten טפחים tfachim high. So less than
four טפחים tfachim doesn't carve out for itself a significant place, like
it's not a space unto itself, okay? It's in a space, but
it's not covering a space itself. So that's not significant enough.
So לא גזרינן, lo gazrinan, that's not included in the גזירה. gezeira.
ומר סבר, u'mar savar, the other says no, כיון דנפיק ליה מתורת
לבוד, keivan d'nafik lei mitoras lavud, once it's more than three then
it's not then
or three or more, less than three is like לבוד, lavud, is
like the air doesn't even exist, right, it's like things are connected
within three. But three or more, it already is a
significant, you can't say לבוד lavud with this space. So therefore it's
a significant width, so גזרינן, gazrinan, and therefore it's part of the
גזירה. gezeira. Okay. So therefore it's interesting how they don't have a
debate about whether it looks like a roof or not, right, like
everybody says that planks four טפחים tfachim wide people use for roofs.
The debate is whether people use, how much people use between three
and four, right? So this is by the way classic in the
גמרא, Gemara, that although the reason is a very pragmatic concern of
what it looks like, once it becomes a halachic issue, we start
applying like very conceptual, formalist categories to it. What would be a
problem of roof? Is it the size of a מקום makom or
is it the size of לבוד, lavud, that determines what size plank
is going to be a problem for this concern about looking like
roof?
Okay. It's pretty wide, it seems to me. In other words, two
טפחים, tfachim, a plank? Yeah, yeah.
But how big would your planks be for your rooftop? I don't
know, I don't know, yeah. But you're right, I mean it's not
insignificant. I wouldn't call, I wouldn't call
ten inches a stick, right? And the גמרא's Gemara phrasing of קני
בעלמא, kani b'alma, again it's sort of like real halachic man. It
doesn't look at it like how people look at it. Oh, but
through a halachic lens, anything less than three טפחים tfachim is not
a significant width. It is fascinating. Okay, so.
Yeah, but no one's talking about how close it is to the
wall. No, right down the middle it could be.
Yeah, exactly. To be כשר, kosher it's better that it be close
to the wall. But to be פסול, pasul it could be anywhere.
Okay, alright. So to be כשר, kosher
close to the wall would make it more...
yeah, no. It allows you to bend the wall. It doesn't require
you, but close to the wall allows you to bend the wall
and therefore, even though it's פסול סכך, pasul s'chach to keep the
סוכה sukkah at least כשר kasher, by bending the wall, with the
סכך.
schach, I thought close to the wall would be more like the
roof because you'd have the three טפחים tfachim with the wall.
Yeah, no, that doesn't seem to be a concern. Continued out. Yeah,
we'll see that, no, that doesn't seem to be the concern. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so this is two ways
of explaining the debate, either categorical that it's four טפחים tfachim and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't care at all about this issue, or
that it's a question of the range within three to four טפחים.
tfachim. Now let's see which, how this plays out. תנן, tnan, our
משנה mishnah teaches, נתן עליה נסר שהוא רחב ארבעה טפחים כשרה, nasan
aleha neser shehu rachav arba'a tfachim kashera, if you did four טפחים
tfachim it's כשר, kasher, ובלבד שלא יישן תחתיו, u'vilvad shelo yishan tachtav,
but don't sleep under it. Now that's said anonymously, so it sounds
a little bit from the משנה mishnah that everybody agrees to this.
בשלמא לשמואל, bishlama l'Shmuel, according to שמואל Shmuel this works, דאמר בשאין
בהן ארבעה מחלוקת, d'amar b'she'ein bahen arba'a machlokes, they're only debating less
than four טפחים. tfachim. אבל יש בהן ארבעה דברי הכל פסולה, avel
yesh bahen arba'a divrei hakol pesula, but once it's four טפחים, tfachim,
everybody says it's פסול. pasul, משום הכי לא יישן תחתיו, mishum hachi
lo yishan tachtav, so there we have it, it's four טפחים, tfachim,
everybody agrees it's פסול, pasul. and it tells you the סוכה sukkah
can be כשר, kasher again I'm reading this through רש"י. Rashi. The
סוכה sukkah can be כשר kasher, if you put it against the
wall
because then it's a bending wall, but don't sleep under it.
אלא לרב, ela l'Rav, according to רב Rav that says שביש בהן
ארבעה מחלוקת, she'byesh bahen arba'a machlokes, that when it's even when it's
four, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't care about it. אבל
אין בהן ארבעה דברי הכל כשרה, avel ein bahen arba'a divrei hakol
kashera, and less than four everybody would say it's כשר, kasher, so
we're talking about four or bigger, that's the whole debate. And even
there, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't care. So לרבי יהודה למה לא
יישן תחתיו? l'Rabbi Yehuda lama lo yishan tachtav? What's the explanation of
the last line in the משנה, mishnah, why can't you sleep under
it according to רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? So the גמרא Gemara says,
מי סברת דברי הכל היא, mi savart divrei hakol hi, what made
you think the last line of the משנה mishnah was
unanimous? סיפא אתאן לרבי מאיר, seifa asan l'Rabbi Meir, the last line
is part of רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir statement. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir who says it's a problem, says once it's four טפחים tfachim
it's a problem, and don't sleep under it. Okay. תא שמע, ta
shema, let's try to prove this again. שני סדינים מצטרפין, shenei sadinim
mitztarfin, if you have two sheets going across your סוכה, sukkah, and
let's say each sheet פסול סכך passul schach. is only a problem
once it's four טפחים tfachim wide. Okay. Now that doesn't mean individual
pieces of סכך schach could be less than four טפחים. tfachim. If
you have a metal bar, right, that's one. טפח, tefach, it's פסול,
pasul, but it only creates a problem for the סוכה succah if
you have four טפחים tefachim of those metal bars. So let's say
you have a sheet which is פסול passul, because it's woven, it's
מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, and it goes down the length of your
סוכה, succah, but it's not four טפחים tefachim wide, it's only two
טפחים tefachim wide. But then you put another sheet right alongside of
it. Well, will that combine to four טפחים? tefachim? Sure.
You didn't weave
them together, but so what? It's like one metal bar and another
metal bar. They're right next to each other, so of course it
combines to four טפחים tefachim to make a problem, a four טפחים
tefachim of invalid סכך schach. in your סוכה. succah. That's true, but
שני נסרים אין מצטרפין, shnei nesarim ein mitztarfin, two planks of wood
do not combine. Why not? Let's assume that if the issue is
combining to four טפחים, tefachim, then the need to combine means that
each plank is less than four טפחים, tefachim, right? Because the whole
question is, does it create a total of four טפחים tefachim of
פסול סכך. passul schach. So if each plank is less than four
טפחים, tefachim, you have a two טפח tefach wide plank and a
two טפח, tefach, they don't combine because each one by itself is
כשר סכך. kosher sechach Right?
Otherwise you can never have
כשר סכך. kosher sechach What? Right, exactly.
Well, that's what the גמרא gemara says, קנים בעלמא. kanim b'alma. רבי
מאיר אומר אף נסרים כסדינים. Rabbi Meir omer af nesarim k'sadinim. No,
the planks are like sheets, they do combine. So this could be
exactly a scenario
where it's less than four טפחים, tefachim, let's say three טפחים tefachim
wide, and the first opinion would be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
say, I don't care, I don't hold this is a problem. And
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, it is a problem because even
that size combines and is פסול סכך. passul schach So בשלמא לשמואל,
bishlama l'Shmuel, this works according to שמואל Shmuel דאמר בשאין בהן ארבע
מחלוקת, d'amar b'she'ein ban arba machlokes, the debate can be even less
than four טפחים, tefachim, so let's say three טפחים, tefachim, אבל יש
בהן ארבע דברי הכל פסול, aval yesh ban arba divrei hakol passul,
once it's four everybody agrees it's not good. מאי מצטרפין מצטרפין לארבע?
mai mitztarfin mitztarfin l'arba? The debate is perfect. We would be dealing
with a three טפח tefach plank, right, which רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say is okay, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say is no
good, and you have two three טפח tefach planks side by side.
So יהודה Yehuda says each one is fine, good, and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says no, each one is invalid and therefore they combine
and it's more than four טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך passul schach
in the middle.
If they're right next to each other.
If they're right next to each other, right.
How do you get around the situation that
it'll מצטרף mitztaref the entire,
no, it has to be three טפחים, tefachim, right? The debate
only begins to be פסול סכך passul schach. according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir once it's three טפחים. tefachim. So meaning according to שמואל's
Shmuel approach, you could have a plank that's less than four טפחים
tefachim that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say is invalid once it's
three טפחים. tefachim. And therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir could say you
need two three טפח tefach planks next to each other to create
a problem. That works. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda wouldn't be bothered
because it's less than four by itself. אלא לרב דאמר ביש בהן
ארבע מחלוקת, ela l'Rav d'amar b'yesh ban arba machlokes, but רב Rav
says not only does רב Rav say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda never
has a problem, רב Rav says even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir only
has a problem once it's four טפחים. tefachim. So if even רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir only has a problem once it's four טפחים, tefachim,
what do you need to combine with? Right? It's by itself, it's
the four טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך. passul schach. היכי דמי? heichi
dami? What's the case? אי דאית בהו ארבע, ei d'is behu arba,
if the plank has four טפחים, tefachim, אמאי לאצטרופי? amai l'itztarufei? Why
would רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir need to combine it with anything? It's
already four טפחים. tefachim. אי דלית בהו ארבע, ei d'les behu arba,
if it's less than four טפחים, tefachim, אמאי? amai? קנים בעלמא נינהו.
kanim b'alma ninhu. According to you רב, Rav, you're saying
that not only does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda not have a problem
at all, but even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't have a problem
unless it's four טפחים. tefachim. So what's the case? We have to
be talking about four טפחים tefachim according to you, so what's the
combining? לעולם דאית בהו ארבע, olam d'is behu arba, there is
four טפחים. tefachim. ומאי מצטרפין מצטרפין לארבע אמות מן
הצד, u'mai mitztarfin mitztarfin l'arba amos min hatzad, because it's combining a
lot of planks so you have so much, you have ארבע אמות
arba amos from the side, you can't even say דופן עקומה. dofen
akuma. Okay? You got it?
Here's your סוכה, succah,
right? Now, we initially thought that what's the case? You've got a
plank of three טפחים tefachim alongside another plank of three טפחים, tefachim,
right? And they combine to make a four טפח tefach problem, because
it's only a problem if you have four טפחים tefachim of פסול
סכך. passul schach. And that's possible if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
less than four טפחים tefachim can be a problematic plank. But if
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that only four טפחים tefachim can be
a problematic plank, you don't need it to combine. Once you have
a four טפח tefach plank, you already have four טפחים tefachim of
פסול סכך. pasul sechach What would be the issue? And the גמרא
gemara says the issue is you put it along the side. If
you're putting these planks along the side, then even though each one
is four טפחים, tefachim, the סוכה succah remains כשר kasher because you
just do the דופן עקומה. dofen akuma. But if you keep on
putting them so much that you now have ארבע אמות, arba amos,
right, now you can no longer do the דופן עקומה. dofen akuma.
The דופן עקומה dofen akuma only goes up to ארבע אמות. arba
amos. So what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is if you
put these planks along the side, it will combine so much to
make ארבע אמות arba amos and stop you from saying דופן עקומה.
dofen akuma.
So ארבע אמות arba amos is another way of saying דופן עקומה,
dofen akuma,
the limit of דופן עקומה. dofen akuma. Okay, so anyway, so that's
what we said. According to רב Rav *Rav*, they're debating four טפח
tefach *Tefach* planks, and even so, they're debating whether they combine, meaning
do they combine from the side? That would be the only time
according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir... *Rebbi Meir* you would need this
to combine. לשנא אחרינא *Lishna achrina*, another way of saying they're debating
is the following or arguing this point is the following. בשלמא *Bishlama*
לשמואל *le-Shmuel* דאמר בשאין בהן ארבע מחלוקת *de-amar beshein bein arba mahlokes*,
according to שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* says less than four, אבל יש בהן
ארבע דברי הכל פסולה *aval yesh bein arba divrei ha-kol pesula*, once
it's four everybody agrees it's פסולה *pesula*, מאי מצטרפין מצטרפין לארבע אמות
מן הצד *mai mitztarfin mitztarfin le-arba amos min ha-tzad*? Again, it's interesting
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it was starting with this. We'll talk
about three טפח tefach *Tefach* planks according to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* and
the issue is could it combine to four טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* in
the middle or could it combine to being four אמות *Amos* from
the side? Either way. אלא לרב *Ela le-Rav*, but according to רב
Rav, *Rav*, בשלמא לרבי מאיר *bishlama le-Rebbi Meir*, we get רבי מאיר
*Rebbi Meir*. מאי מצטרפין מצטרפין לארבע אמות מן הצד *mai mitztarfin mitztarfin
le-arba amos min ha-tzad*. We're talking about four טפח tefach *Tefach* planks
and רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says it's a problem, it'll combine, combine
for what purpose? To be four אמות *Amos* from the side. אלא
רבי יהודה דאמר אפילו יש בהן ארבע כשירה *Ela Rebbi Yehuda de-amar
afilu yesh bein arba kesheira*, but according to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*
that says even at four טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* it's כשירה *kesheira*, מאי
אין מצטרפין *mai ein mitztarfin*? Why would you have to say they
don't combine? What do you mean they don't combine? קני בעלמא נינהו
*Kanei be-alma ninhu*. They're just sticks, just tell me they're not פסול
passul סכך s'chach. *pasul s'chach*. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says yeah, but איידי
דקאמר רבי מאיר מצטרפין אמר רבי יהודה אין מצטרפין *aidei de-ka-amar Rebbi
Meir mitztarfin amar Rebbi Yehuda ein mitztarfin*. Since מאיר *Meir* says they
combine, יהודה *Yehuda* says they don't combine. So it's basically the same
point. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, look, according to רב *Rav*
we're talking about four טפח tefach *Tefach* planks and רבי מאיר *Rebbi
Meir* says they combine to be four אמות *Amos* from the side.
That's רבי מאיר מצטרפין *Rebbi Meir mitztarfin*. Why does רבי יהודה *Rebbi
Yehuda* say אין מצטרפין *ein mitztarfin*? רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* should be
saying about this is it's all כשר סכך kosher sechach, *kosher s'chach*.
So says you're right, he could have said it's all כשר kasher,
סכך s'chach *kosher s'chach*, but since רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says it
combine, he says it doesn't combine, but in the end of the
day רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* really holds that it is all
כשר kosher סכך schach *kosher s'chach*. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרב תניא כוותיה
דשמואל *tanya ke-vassa de-Rav tanya ke-vassa de-Shmuel*. We have a ברייתא *Baraita*
that supports each position. תניא כוותיה דרב *Tanya ke-vassa de-Rav*, we taught
like רב *Rav*. סיככה בנסרים של ארז *Sichechah bi-nesarim shel erez*, if
you used cedar planks, like real like permanent, שאין בהם ארבע *she-ein
ba-hem arba*, less than four טפחים tfachim *Tefachim*, דברי הכל כשירה *divrei
ha-kol kesheira*. It explicitly says like רב *Rav*, less than four טפחים
tfachim *Tefachim* everybody says it's okay. יש בהם ארבע רבי מאיר פוסל
רבי יהודה מכשיר *yesh ba-hem arba Rebbi Meir posel Rebbi Yehuda machshir*.
רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* invalidates and רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* says it's
valid. אמר רבי יהודה *Amar Rebbi Yehuda*, says רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*,
מעשה בשעת הסכנה *ma'aseh bi-she'at ha-sakana*, there was a time where it
was a time of danger, meaning that there was an edict from
the non-Jews and that they could not build a סוכה sukkah, *Sukkah*,
maybe who knows
even at persecution or death, so there was no so they weren't
allowed to sit in a סוכה sukkah *Sukkah*. So what did they
do? שהביאנו נסרים שהיו בהן ארבע *she-heivianu nesarim she-hayu bein arba*, we,
it's quite interesting he talks in the we, the plural, right? רבי
יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* was a student of רבי עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva*, right?
רבי עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva* was the Herodian persecution. So it's interesting that
this שעת הסכנה *she'at ha-sakana* seems to be something that he actually
experienced. So what did we do? We brought brought some planks that
were four טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* wide וסיככנו על גבי מרפסת וישבנו תחתיהן
*ve-sichachnu gabei mirpeset ve-yashavnu tachteihen*, and we put it on top of
our porch and we dwelt under it. So they didn't realize that
we were living in a סוכה sukkah. *Sukkah*, we fooled the Romans,
right, you got the scenario, right? We basically put planks, we made
it look like we're having a covered portico, and technically it was
a כשר kosher סוכה sukkah *kosher Sukkah*. And those planks were four
טפחים tfachim *Tefachim*, so you see four טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* is okay.
אמרו לו *Amru lo*, so they have an obvious response, משם ראיה
*mi-sham re'ayah*? You want to bring a proof from there? אין שעת
הסכנה ראיה *ein she'at ha-sakana re'ayah*. What we allow at the time
of persecution is not a proof of what the general הלכה halacha
*halacha* is. Fascinating little historical note, but again relevant that according to
רב *Rav* it's clear they only or goes like רב *Rav*, they're
only arguing four טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* or bigger.
תניא כוותיה דשמואל *tanya ke-vassa de-Shmuel*,
we taught like שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. סיככה בנסרים של ארז *sichechah bi-nesarim
shel erez*, if you use these again planks of cedar, שיש בהן
ארבע *she-yesh ba-hem arba*, once it's four טפחים *Tefachim* according to this
ברייתא דברי הכל פסולה *Baraita divrei ha-kol pesula*, everybody says it's invalid.
אין בהן ארבע *ein ba-hem arba*, if it doesn't have four, ורבי
מאיר פוסל ורבי יהודה מכשיר *ve-Rebbi Meir posel ve-Rebbi Yehuda machshir*, that's
the debate. ומודה רבי מאיר *U-modeh Rebbi Meir*, now even though רבי
מאיר *Rebbi Meir* invalidates, he admits שאם יש בין נסר לנסר כמלא
נסר *she-im yesh bein neser le-neser k'mlo neser*, that if there's a
gap between one plank and the other the size of a plank
שמניח פסל psal, ביניהן *she-meniach pesal beineihen*, again fascinating that the word
for כשר סכך sechach? *kosher s'chach* is פסל psal *pesal*, פסולת גורן
ויקב *pesoles goren ve-yekev*, you put כשר סכך sechach *kosher s'chach* between
them, כשירה *kesheira*, and it's kosher. We're going to deal with this
later, but the basic idea here is in fact if you have,
right, this is your plank and this is your plank and this
is your plank, right, and you have this
and you have כשר סכך sechach *kosher s'chach* between
them, so you know now that's kosher. Now why? You'd say it's
fifty-fifty even if it's a row of כשר סכך sechach *kosher s'chach*
but it's not intermingled, why does it become kosher? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to do a scenario that you actually start
at opposite ends of the סוכה sukkah *Sukkah*, so in the middle
you have by doing in between since you're a little bit off
starting at opposite ends. you have in the middle you have two
of these things of כשר *kosher* which is eight טפחים *tefachim* which
is the size of a כשר סוכה sukkah. *kosher sukkah* and somehow
that makes and then you bend the wall up to it. You
sort of see what you do? You do the bending wall up
to this point and
then you get the bending wall up to this
point and that's the כשר *kosher*.
Oh, I guess that depends on how wide your סוכה sukkah *sukkah*
is.
Exactly. Anyway, that's how the גמרא *Gemara* would explain it, but that's
not our interest right now. Okay, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would agree
to that case. ומודה רבי יהודה *Umodeh Rabbi Yehuda*, and רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* would agree, שאם נתן עליה נסר שרחב ארבעה טפחים *she’im
natan aleha neser sherachav arba’ah tefachim*, כשרה *k’sherah*, that even though רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is lenient and says that, you know, that sometimes
these planks are כשר *kosher* if they're less than four, once it's
four, it can be כשר *kosher* in the, it is true, it
can be כשר *kosher* if you put it on the side, but
אין ישנים תחתיו *ein yeshenin tachtav*, you can't sleep under it. So
even רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* admits, the one who's מקיל *meikil*, would
agree that you can't sleep under it. והישן תחתיו לא Lo, יצא
ידי חובתו *v’hayashen tachtav lo yatza yedei chovato*, and if you do,
you didn't fulfill your obligation. Okay, so there we have the debate
of רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel*. Are they debating four and bigger?
According to רב *Rav*, one ברייתא *baraita* explicitly says that's the only
debate. Are they debating between three and four? But once it's four,
everybody agrees it's invalid. That's another ברייתא *baraita*. And the ברייתא *baraita*
ended, we're not going to worry about this case of alternating, by
saying that what the משנה *Mishnah* says, which is, is that your
סוכה sukkah *sukkah* will remain כשר *kosher*, okay, if you, again, the
way רש"י *Rashi* explains it, you put it at the side, do
the bending wall, the סוכה sukkah *sukkah* will remain כשר *kosher*, but
you can't sleep under it because now it constitutes a wall.
Did they decide which debate is right? Exactly. The big question is
which debate, which debate is the correct debate.
Then we have to figure out how we פסקן *pasken*. Right. So
we'll do, I'll say a minute about that at the end. Let's
just finish to the end of the דף *daf*. I think we
can do it. Okay, אתמר *itmar*, it was taught. הפכן על צדיהן
*Hafkhan al tzideihen*. You took these four טפח tefach *tefach* planks, which
are פסול pasul *pasul*, and you rotated them 90 degrees and you're
going to use it on סכך sechach *schach*, but you're going to
use it, right? Here's your plank, here's your פסול pasul *pasul* plank,
but you're going to put it on your סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* not
like a plank, but you're going to put it on your סוכה
sukkah *sukkah* like this. Okay, will that be כשר *kosher* now? So
רב הונא אמר פסולה *Rav Huna amar psulah*. רב הונא *Rav Huna*
says it remains invalid. ורב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא אמרי כשרה
*v’Rav Chisda v’Rabba bar Rav Huna amri k’sherah*, and רב חסדא *Rav
Chisda* and רבה בר רב הונא *Rabba bar Rav Huna*, רב הונא
*Rav Huna*’s son, said it was כשר *kosher*. So איקלע רב נחמן
לסורא *ikla Rav Nachman l’Sura*. Now they're all in סורא *Sura*. רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman* was visiting סורא *Sura*. So ולגבי *u’l’gabbei* רב חסדא
*Rav Chisda* ורבה בר רב הונא *v’Rabba bar Rav Huna*, who said
it was כשר *kosher*, went to visit רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*, try
to get him involved in this debate. אמרי ליה *amri lei*, they
said to him, הפכן על צדיהן מהו *hafkhan al tzideihen mahu*? What
would be the story if you would turn the plank of wood
on its side? Would it be כשר *kosher*, which is what they
would say? אמר להו *amar lehu*, he said to them, פסולה *psulah*.
No, it remains invalid. נעשו כשפודים של מתכת *na’asu k’shfudim shel matechet*.
Once the rabbis said you can't use a plank, then you have
to treat it like פסול pasul סכך sechach *pasul schach*. You have
to treat it like a metal bar, right? It doesn't matter that
in this configuration it's not ארבעה טפחים *arba'ah tefachim* wide, or people
normally don't make a roof with planks turned 90 degrees. Once the
rabbis said the plank was invalid, then they gave it a full
status of invalid סכך *schach*. And then it doesn't matter how you
put it on your סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. אמר להו רב הונא *amar
lehu Rav Huna*, so רב הונא *Rav Huna* said to these two
rabbis who debated him, one being his son, לא אמרי לכו אמרי
כוותי *lo amari l’chu amri k’vasi*? Hey, haha, I was right. Didn't
I tell you you should say like me? You see that? רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman* agrees with me. He says it's invalid. אמרו ליה
*amru lei*, they said to him, ומי אמר לן מר טעמא ולא
קבלינא מיניה *u’mi amar lan mar ta’ama v’lo kablina minei*? Yeah, but
he gave, רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* gave us a reason. You know,
you said oh, listen to me, but you didn't give us a
reason. If you had ever given us a reason and then we
didn't listen to you? So you see that he told us why.
אמר להו *amar lehu*, he said back to them, ומי בעיתו מיני
טעמא ולא אמרי לכו *u’mi bayisu minei ta’ama v’lo amari l’chu*? Have
you ever asked me for a reason and I didn't tell you?
If you wanted a reason, you should have asked. Fascinating. I've had
arguments like that. Okay, so now we see that even if you
turn it on its side, it's no good, because once the rabbis
invalidated it, they made it really like פסול סכך *pasul schach*. לימא
מסייע ליה *leima m’saye’a lei*, let me bring a proof to this
idea that it doesn't matter, that it remains invalid. אין מחזקת כדי
ראשו ורובו ושולחנו *ein machazeket k’dei rosho v’rubo v’shulchano*. If a סוכה
sukkah, *sukkah* cannot hold your body and your table, less than seven
by seven טפחים *tefachim*. או שנפרצה בה פרצה כדי שיזקר בה גדי
בבת ראש *o shenifretzah bah pirtzah k’dei sheyizaker bah gdi b’vat rosh*,
or there's a gap between the wall and the floor. And there's
a, you know, and it's been breached. And the size of that
gap is the size that a little kid goat could run underneath
it, which basically is שלשה טפחים *shlosha tefachim*. Okay, so meaning if
your wall is שלשה טפחים *shlosha tefachim* off of the ground, then
you can't say לבוד *lavud* and it no longer serves as a
wall, a goat could run under it. So that'll be invalid. או
*o*, here's the third way of invalidating, שנתן עליה נסר שרחב ארבעה
טפחים *shenatan aleha neser sherachav arba’ah tefachim*, you put a plank that's
ארבעה טפחים *arba’ah tefachim* wide on it. אף על פי שלא הכניס
לתוכה אלא שלשה טפחים פסולה *af al pi shelo hichnis l’tocha ella
shlosha tefachim, psulah*. Even though only שלשה טפחים *shlosha tefachim* are covering
the סכך *schach*, it remains invalid. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, היכי
דמי Heichi dami *heichi dami*? Well, that's how you're explaining it, but
the גמרא *Gemara* initially didn't understand that. The גמרא *Gemara* says... היכי
דמי wait that's off the top well that's how you're explaining it
but the גמרא initially didn't understand that. The גמרא says היכי דמי
what's the case that it's a four טפח tefach wide and only
three טפחים are covering the סכך? לאו כשהפכן על צידיהן? Lav k'shehafchan
al tzideiyan? Wouldn't it be you turn it on its side? Of
course think about what a piece of wood would have to look
like like that.
Four טפחים wide one way, which
is like a foot, and three טפחים and nine inches the other
way, that is like a huge cinderblock. Well it's like those big
beams, right. So isn't that the case? So you see even when
you turn it on its side it's no good. לא, no, הכא
במאי עסקינן hacha b'mai askinan what are we talking about? כגון דאנח
kegon de'anach like Michael said אפומא דמטללתא, apuma d'metallelta, you put it
flat four טפחים but you put it right by the door of
the סוכה, sukkah. דעייל תלתא לגב ואפיק חד לבר, de'ayeil tlata l'gav
ve'afik chad l'var, three in the סוכה sukkah and one's out of
the סוכה. sukkah. Right, you got the scenario? Yeah, it's very simple,
right? You put it here. Here's
your three walls of the סוכה and you put the beam here
like this. Three טפחים are in the סוכה and one טפח tefach
is outside of the סוכה. Okay, and now this is going to
try to defend the approach that you need four טפחים the normal
way to be invalid. So if that's true why is it invalid?
If only three of the four טפחים are in the סוכה why
don't we call it a three טפח beam? So it says דהוה
ליה פסל היוצא מן הסוכה וכל פסל היוצא מן הסוכה, dehavah leh
psal hayotzei min hasukkah vechol psal hayotzei min hasukkah, it's like סכך
that goes out of the סוכה and any סכך that goes out
of the סוכה נידון כסוכה nidon kesukkah is like סוכה, meaning the
normal הלכה is that if this were כשר סכך and a little
bit was extending beyond the opening of the סוכה and you were
sitting underneath this כשר סכך outside of the סוכה but it extended
off on the edge of the סוכה, right? And this was an
open doorway this third wall that would be like you're in the
סוכה. So the extension of the סכך פסל, which is the word
they use for כשר סכך, the extension of the סכך outside the
סוכה makes things under the סכך like it's in the סוכה. So
if that's true to be כשר it's also true to be פסול
and I could tell you a four טפח beam is only פסול
when it's aligned in the four טפח way and nevertheless this is
פסול because it's an extension outside, it's like it's all inside and
you look at it as a four טפח
as a full four טפח beam. So that's how you could defend
it but the conclusion seems very clearly that even if you reorient
it it remains invalid. Once חז"ל Chazal invalidated it they treated it
like these metal bars, meaning totally פסול סכך and it doesn't matter
how you orient it. In terms by the way of how you
rule do we what do we rule about this like רב or
שמואל, what is the debate? So if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says it seems from the פשט pshat of
this גמרא that we rule like שמואל interpretation of the debate. Even
though normally by these types of things we normally go by רב,
he infers from the גמרא we go like שמואל and therefore even
between three and four טפחים it would remain part of the debate.
Okay so we'll end with that. Yes, you have a question.
Why is it called a פסל is it
you mean רבי מאיר...